Guide to the Fra Broadwell Dana Papers 1819-1947
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Fra Broadwell Dana Papers
1819-1947
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 096
Dana, Fra Broadwell, 1874-1948
1.5 linear feet
The Broadwell and Dana families included an important Montana artist, Fra Dana, and a significant ranching business. This collection contains genealogical information on many branches from Fra Broadwell's family and Edwin Dana's family.
Biographical Note
Fra Marie Broadwell was born Nov. 26, 1874, in Terra Haute, Indiana. Soon afeeter this she moved with her family to Rockville, Indiana, where she lived until she was 16 years old. She was then sent to Cincinnati to study painting; from there she went to New York where she attended the American Art School as a pupil of William M. Chase. She later continued her art studies in Paris, where she was a pupil of Alfred Maurer. In 1891 she first went to Wyoming where her mother, who had remarried, lived. Her second trip to Wyoming was in 1893, where she met her future husband, Edwin Lester Dana. They married July 1, 1896. She was a collector of art and several pieces of the collection were willed to the University of Montana. Mrs. Dana died Dec. 1, 1948, in Great Falls, Montana, where she is buried.
Edwin Lester Dana was born October 15, 1864, and his family moved to Montana in 1866. They lived first in Philipsburg, then Missoula, then Helena. In 1878 the family moved to a cattle ranch on the Little Big Horn River in southeastern Montana, where Edwin began his cattle business. He bought his first small herd in 1887. By 1918 he owned one of the largest pure bred Hereford cattle herds in America. Mr. Dana owned a ranch in Parkman, Wyoming, and later, a second one in Cascade County, Montana. Mrs. Dana was his secretary and keen business partner in spite of her frail health. E.L. Dana died in 1946.
This collection contains genealogical information on many branches from Fra Broadwell's family and Edwin Dana's family. There is correspondence from family members to Fra and Edwin about their families histories. Some of the families that have excellent research included are lines from the Anderson, Brewster, Broadwell, Dana, Forester, Maxwell, Page, Paine, Putnam, and Sunderland families, although this does not include all of the lines researched in this collection. There are copied accounts from family members early history, and publications on the Paine and Dana family.
Fra Dana also had publications on Astrology and scientific papers. There are also notes on the Crow language from Father Prando and Fra's own notes. Included also is a brand book of the cattle herd of the Blackfoot, which was purchased by E.L. Dana.
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Genealogical, 0.7 linear feet, 1819-1938
Series II: Research Material, 0.7 linear feet, 1850-1947
Series III: Photographs, 0.1 linear feet, undated
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Gift of Fra Broadwell Dana, date unknown.
Family papers--Montana; Genealogies--Montana
Blackfoot Indians; Astrology; Cattle brands--Montana; Crow Indians; Sihasapa Indians--Domestic animals--Montana
Anderson family; Brewster family; Broadwell family; Dana family; Forester family; Foster family; Maxwell family; Page family; Paine family; Payne family; Putnam family; Sunderland family
Montana; Fine Arts; Native Americans
Dana, E. L. (Edwin Lester), 1864-1946
- Genealogical, 1819-1938; Series I; 0.7 linear feet
  This series includes all of the genealogical information Fra Dana was able to gather on family descent. There are twenty-six families researched in this collection. Included is a direct line decent of Fra Broadwell Dana. There are several marriage certificates. These include the certificate for the marriage of John Sunderland to Elizabeth Page on February 14, 1819, a certificate for Samuel F. Maxwell and Eliza Ann Sunderland on November 8, 1848, a certificate for John W. Broadwell and Jewel H. Maxwell's marriage on May 12, 1873, and the marriage of E.L. Dana to Fra Broadwell on July 1, 1896. Parts of a will for E.L. Dana dated to 1916 are included and a copy of the will for Ann E. Broadwell dated to May 14, 1889, copied November 18, 1912 are included. There are also applications to the Daughters of the American Revolution for Jessie A. Sunderland (1899) and Emma R. Griffin (1909). The Paine and Dana lines also have published material on their families.
  - Genealogical letters, 1899-1933 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Anderson line, undated, 1912, 1914, 1933 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Andrew line, undated (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Andrews line, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Brewster line, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Broadwell line, undated, 1873, 1941 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Fra Broadwell Dana's direct line, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Chappel line, 1935 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Dana family history (reprint), undated (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Dana line, 1911-1914, 1927, 1933-1934, 1938 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Legal Documents, 1896, 1916 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Deacon line, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Dinwiddie line, undated (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Dunn line, undated (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Dunster line, undated (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Forester line, undated (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Foster line, undated (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Hathorne line, undated (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Jackson line, undated, 1912 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Lawrence line, undated (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Maxwell line, 1848, from document dated 1886, 1899, 1909, 1911-1914, 1916, 1938 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Morse line, undated (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Page line, undated, 1916 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Paine family publications, volume 1, numbers 1-8 dating 1879-1881, volume 2, numbers 1-12 dating 1882-1883 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Paine line, undated (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Peabody (Paybody) line, undated (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Porter line, undated (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Putnam line, undated (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Sunderland line, undated, 1819, 1898, 1900, 1912-1916 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Ver Planck line, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Miscellaneous Genealogical researched material, undated (Box-folder 2/3)
- Research Material, 1850-1947; Series II; 0.7 linear feet
  This series includes copies of accounts from early family history from various family members, such as H.W. Baldwin (1895-1897), M.A. Whipple (undated, 1935), Abraham Given (1850) and Theophilus and Debora Dana (1862). Poems written by E.L. Dana (published 1947) and Edna Dinwiddie (copy undated) are also included. There are copies of letters (undated, 1914, 1917-1918) from World War I and papers (1915, 1917, 1926) from World War I--correspondents are not identified by last name. There is a certificate from the Daughters of the American Revolution (D.A.R.) and Colonial Dames of America (undated, 1911-1912). Jewel Dinwiddie's Daughters of the American Revolution pin and tartan are in this collection as well. Family newspaper clippings are also included. This series also includes notes on the Crow language from Father Prando and Fra Dana and the brand book for the Blackfoot herd of cattle (undated).
  - Miscellaneous Astrology papers and scientific papers, 1887, 1888, 1890, 1899, 1901, 1902, 1907, 1925 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Baldwin, H.W., Early Day Camping Trips (copy, remembered to 1895-1897), undated (Box-folder 2/5)
  - D.A.R certificates and Colonial Dames of America, undated, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - D.A.R pin and tartan, undated (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Diary entry copied from Aunt Lou (entry dated 1862), undated (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Dinwiddie, Edna- Poems, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Account of 1871 Christmas Ball in Rockville, Indiana (copy), undated (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Whipple, M.A.- Twenty-five Years In Persia (copy), undated, 1931 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - World War I letters (copy), undated, 1914-1918 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - World War I papers, 1915-1926 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Publications, 1882-1903 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Family newspaper clippings, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Newspaper clippings from Rockville, Indiana, undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Mrs. Dana's list of collection contents, undated (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Poems of E.L. Dana, 1947 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Bound but unpublished books of poems by E.L. Dana which also contains 4 letters by Fra Dana to Dean Crowder and an autobiography written by E.L. Dana, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Reminiscence titled "An Overland Trip to California in 1850" by Abraham Given (copy), undated (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Reminiscences of an overland trip to California in 1862, by Theophilus and Debora Dana (copy), undated (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Grammar and notes on the Crow Language, by Father Prando, undated (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Grammar and notes on the Crow Language, by Fra Dana, undated (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Brand book of the cattle from the Blackfoot, undated (Box-folder 3/11)
- Photographs, undated; Series III; 0.1 linear feet
  - Two women by tombstone of John Broadwell, undated; 96(III)1 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Two Sunderland tombstones, undated; 96(III)2 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Three tombstones, undated; 96(III)3 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - John Sunderland's tombstone, undated; 96(III)4 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Nancy and Elizabeth Sunderland's tombstones, undated; 96(III)5 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Woman in bonnet and man in suitcoat, undated; 96(III)6 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Man with beard, undated; 96(III)7 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Woman seated in chair, undated; 96(III)8 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - 96(III)9, undated; Woman and child (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Man with mustache, undated; 96(III)10 (Box-folder 3/21)